<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-20T15:34:11+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">vonMentzer-Group</title><subtitle>Website of the von Mentzer Group at the University of Gothenburg, led by Dr Astrid von Mentzer.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Welcome new postdoc - Biel Puigserver</title><link href="/2025/02/03/newcomer-Biel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome new postdoc - Biel Puigserver" /><published>2025-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-20T15:33:17+00:00</updated><id>/2025/02/03/newcomer-Biel</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/02/03/newcomer-Biel.html"><![CDATA[<p><br />
We are very excited to announce that Biel Puigserver has joined the lab!
<br />
Biel comes from a veterinary background with expertise in both wet-and bioinformatics. He will be involved in computational projects investigating the Evolution of E. coli. 
<br /></p>]]></content><author><name>Astrid von Mentzer</name></author><category term="newcomers" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are very excited to announce that Biel Puigserver has joined the lab! Biel comes from a veterinary background with expertise in both wet-and bioinformatics. He will be involved in computational projects investigating the Evolution of E. coli.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Visiting ETH-Zurich and the</title><link href="/2024/12/03/visit-ETHZ.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visiting ETH-Zurich and the" /><published>2024-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-20T15:33:17+00:00</updated><id>/2024/12/03/visit-ETHZ</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/12/03/visit-ETHZ.html"><![CDATA[<p><br />
<br />
Last year, Prof. Dr. Marie Schölmerich reached out for help with the shipment of samples collected from the pristine wetlands in Värmland. I was happy to assist a fellow female researcher, and after some logistical challenges—including a few lost samples—most of them finally arrived safely in Zurich.</p>

<p>Recently, I had the opportunity to visit Marie’s lab at ETH Zurich, where I gave a talk on colonisation factors in E. coli. It was a great chance to discuss ongoing research and explore potential collaborations on metagenomic sequencing of the Värmland samples. The data holds exciting potential for understanding microbial communities in these unique environments, and I’m looking forward to working together on this.
<br />
Beyond science, we also talked about the challenges of setting up a new lab as junior PIs—covering everything from recruitment to lab organisation. Marie shared invaluable insights, and I’ve already started implementing some of her advice in the von Mentzer Lab.
<br />
It was a fantastic visit filled with engaging discussions, new ideas, and valuable takeaways. Looking forward to future collaborations!
<br />
<br />
Read more on about the research in Schölmerich Lab: <a href="[https://meetings.embo.org/event/23-amr-plasmids](https://ibp.ethz.ch/people/person-detail.MzMyOTU4.TGlzdC82NjcsLTE0MzQwMTkxMjA=.html)">Schölmerich Lab</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Astrid von Mentzer</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last year, Prof. Dr. Marie Schölmerich reached out for help with the shipment of samples collected from the pristine wetlands in Värmland. I was happy to assist a fellow female researcher, and after some logistical challenges—including a few lost samples—most of them finally arrived safely in Zurich.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome Esmee and Melek - new students!</title><link href="/2024/08/06/newcomers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome Esmee and Melek - new students!" /><published>2024-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-20T15:33:17+00:00</updated><id>/2024/08/06/newcomers</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/08/06/newcomers.html"><![CDATA[<p><br />
We are delighted to welcome two new students to the von Mentzer Lab!
<br />
<strong>Esmee Shenkeveld - MSc-student</strong>
<br />
We are pleased to introduce our new MSc student, Esmee, who will be focusing on investigating a recently identified colonisation factor, CS23. Her research will delve into the plasmids carrying CS23 from isolates collected in Bolivia, spanning both patients and the environment. This important work aims to enhance our understanding of how CS23 contributes to <em>E. coli</em> colonisation and its implications for public health. 
<br />
<strong>Melek Ebrar Emer - Erasmus-student</strong>
<br />
We are also thrilled to welcome an Erasmus student, Melek, who will be part of our lab for the next semester. Melek will be working on a large-scale project invetsigating the plasmidome of ETEC.
<br /></p>]]></content><author><name>Astrid von Mentzer</name></author><category term="newcomers" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are delighted to welcome two new students to the von Mentzer Lab! Esmee Shenkeveld - MSc-student We are pleased to introduce our new MSc student, Esmee, who will be focusing on investigating a recently identified colonisation factor, CS23. Her research will delve into the plasmids carrying CS23 from isolates collected in Bolivia, spanning both patients and the environment. This important work aims to enhance our understanding of how CS23 contributes to E. coli colonisation and its implications for public health. Melek Ebrar Emer - Erasmus-student We are also thrilled to welcome an Erasmus student, Melek, who will be part of our lab for the next semester. Melek will be working on a large-scale project invetsigating the plasmidome of ETEC.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Keynote lecture at the ECMIS conference in Ghent</title><link href="/2024/07/01/ECMIS.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Keynote lecture at the ECMIS conference in Ghent" /><published>2024-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-20T15:33:17+00:00</updated><id>/2024/07/01/ECMIS</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/07/01/ECMIS.html"><![CDATA[<p><br />
I’m are excited to share that I recently gave a keynote lecture at the E. coli and Mucosal Immune Systems (ECMIS) Conference in Ghent. The topic of the lecture was “Colonisation Factors in E. coli,” an area of research that is both fascinating and vital to understanding bacterial pathogenesis.
<br />
We delved into the history of the nomenclature of adhesins, shedding light on the complexities and evolution of the terminology over the years. We also discussed the first visualisation of adhesins using transmission electron microscopy, marking a significant milestone in microbiology.
<br />
Additionally, I presented a summary of the latest research from our lab, which investigates colonisation factors across E. coli using large-scale genetic analyses. This cutting-edge research is helping to uncover new insights into how these factors contribute to bacterial colonisation and infection.
<br />
It was really exciting to give my first keynote lecture and I was happy to see some old friends at the conference too!
<br />
<br />
Stay tuned for more updates and detailed findings from our ongoing research!
<br /></p>]]></content><author><name>Astrid von Mentzer</name></author><category term="conference" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m are excited to share that I recently gave a keynote lecture at the E. coli and Mucosal Immune Systems (ECMIS) Conference in Ghent. The topic of the lecture was “Colonisation Factors in E. coli,” an area of research that is both fascinating and vital to understanding bacterial pathogenesis. We delved into the history of the nomenclature of adhesins, shedding light on the complexities and evolution of the terminology over the years. We also discussed the first visualisation of adhesins using transmission electron microscopy, marking a significant milestone in microbiology. Additionally, I presented a summary of the latest research from our lab, which investigates colonisation factors across E. coli using large-scale genetic analyses. This cutting-edge research is helping to uncover new insights into how these factors contribute to bacterial colonisation and infection. It was really exciting to give my first keynote lecture and I was happy to see some old friends at the conference too! Stay tuned for more updates and detailed findings from our ongoing research!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">von Mentzer Lab receives funding from Jeanssons Stiftelse</title><link href="/2023/12/01/fund-jeanssons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="von Mentzer Lab receives funding from Jeanssons Stiftelse" /><published>2023-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-20T15:33:17+00:00</updated><id>/2023/12/01/fund-jeanssons</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/12/01/fund-jeanssons.html"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Astrid von Mentzer</name></author><category term="funding" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Postdoc Scholarship Available - Apply Now!</title><link href="/2023/08/20/postdoc-scholarship1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Postdoc Scholarship Available - Apply Now!" /><published>2023-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-20T15:33:17+00:00</updated><id>/2023/08/20/postdoc-scholarship1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/08/20/postdoc-scholarship1.html"><![CDATA[<p><br />
<br />
<strong>Are you interested in mocrobial genomics, virulence and antibiotic resistance?</strong>
<br />
<strong>Then you need to apply for the Postdoc Scholarship in the von Mentzer Lab!</strong>
<br />
<br />
Join us in experiencing the perfect blend of research and quality of life. Collaborate with leading minds, dive into innovative research, and create lasting connections within Sweden’s dynamic academic community.
<br />
<br />
Beyond academia, Sweden’s commitment to work-life balance ensures you’ll have time to explore the country’s captivating culture and natural beauty.
<br />
<br />
We can’t wait to welcome you to Sweden, where your academic journey will flourish.
<br />
<br />
Ready to seize this opportunity? Read more about our <a href="/Research">Research</a> and the <a href="/Team">Team</a> and how to apply <a href="https://www.nature.com/naturecareers/job/12804554/postdoctoral-scholarship-in-enterotoxigenic-e-coli-etec-genomics-and-evolution/">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Astrid von Mentzer</name></author><category term="job" /><category term="postdoc" /><category term="microbial genomics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Are you interested in mocrobial genomics, virulence and antibiotic resistance? Then you need to apply for the Postdoc Scholarship in the von Mentzer Lab! Join us in experiencing the perfect blend of research and quality of life. Collaborate with leading minds, dive into innovative research, and create lasting connections within Sweden’s dynamic academic community. Beyond academia, Sweden’s commitment to work-life balance ensures you’ll have time to explore the country’s captivating culture and natural beauty. We can’t wait to welcome you to Sweden, where your academic journey will flourish. Ready to seize this opportunity? Read more about our Research and the Team and how to apply here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring AMR - We will participate in the EMBO Plasmid Workshop</title><link href="/2023/08/18/embo-plasmid-workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring AMR - We will participate in the EMBO Plasmid Workshop" /><published>2023-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-20T15:33:17+00:00</updated><id>/2023/08/18/embo-plasmid-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/08/18/embo-plasmid-workshop.html"><![CDATA[<p><br />
<br />
We’re excited to share a lab update! I am gearing up for the EMBO Workshop, a deep dive into plasmid evolution and its connection to antimicrobial resistance (AMR).
<br />
<strong>Decoding Antibiotic Resistance Spread</strong>
<br />
Antimicrobial resistance is a global challenge, with bacteria becoming resistant to antibiotics. Plasmids, tiny genetic carriers, play a role by shuttling resistance genes between bacteria.
<br />
<strong>Unveiling Plasmid Secrets</strong>
<br />
At the EMBO Workshop, we’ll be exploring plasmid biology and ecology. Recent tech advancements allow us to better understand how plasmids contribute to AMR outbreaks.
<br />
<strong>Collaboration for Progress</strong>
The workshop is a hub of experts – from modelers to genetics researchers. I am thrilled to be part of this collaborative effort to address AMR challenges.
<br />
<strong>My Role in the Workshop</strong>
<br />
I’m eager to learn, contribute, and develop fresh approaches to tackle AMR. Stay tuned as we share insights from this enlightening experience.
<br />
<br />
Learn more about the workshop: <a href="https://meetings.embo.org/event/23-amr-plasmids">EMBO Plasmid workshop</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Astrid von Mentzer</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re excited to share a lab update! I am gearing up for the EMBO Workshop, a deep dive into plasmid evolution and its connection to antimicrobial resistance (AMR). Decoding Antibiotic Resistance Spread Antimicrobial resistance is a global challenge, with bacteria becoming resistant to antibiotics. Plasmids, tiny genetic carriers, play a role by shuttling resistance genes between bacteria. Unveiling Plasmid Secrets At the EMBO Workshop, we’ll be exploring plasmid biology and ecology. Recent tech advancements allow us to better understand how plasmids contribute to AMR outbreaks. Collaboration for Progress The workshop is a hub of experts – from modelers to genetics researchers. I am thrilled to be part of this collaborative effort to address AMR challenges. My Role in the Workshop I’m eager to learn, contribute, and develop fresh approaches to tackle AMR. Stay tuned as we share insights from this enlightening experience. Learn more about the workshop: EMBO Plasmid workshop]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Visiting the Thomson Group and joining the Applied Bioinformatics and Public Health Microbiology Conference</title><link href="/2023/05/01/applied_bioinfo_conf_and_meeting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visiting the Thomson Group and joining the Applied Bioinformatics and Public Health Microbiology Conference" /><published>2023-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-20T15:33:17+00:00</updated><id>/2023/05/01/applied_bioinfo_conf_and_meeting</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/05/01/applied_bioinfo_conf_and_meeting.html"><![CDATA[<p>It was a couple of years ago since I attended the <a href="https://coursesandconferences.wellcomeconnectingscience.org/event/applied-bioinformatics-public-health-microbiology-20230503/">Applied Bioinformatics and Public Health Conference</a> organised by Wellcome Connecting Science. Excited to get updated on the latest bioinformatic tools used in microbial genomics. One of the talks I am looking forward to a little bit extra is “Mutational spectra are associated with pathogen niche” by Chris Ruis.</p>]]></content><author><name>astrid_vonmentzer</name></author><category term="WIP," /><category term="conference" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It was a couple of years ago since I attended the Applied Bioinformatics and Public Health Conference organised by Wellcome Connecting Science. Excited to get updated on the latest bioinformatic tools used in microbial genomics. One of the talks I am looking forward to a little bit extra is “Mutational spectra are associated with pathogen niche” by Chris Ruis.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome New Lab Manager - Jeslin Varghese</title><link href="/2023/04/18/new_member_jeslin.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome New Lab Manager - Jeslin Varghese" /><published>2023-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-20T15:33:17+00:00</updated><id>/2023/04/18/new_member_jeslin</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/04/18/new_member_jeslin.html"><![CDATA[<p><br />
We are happy to announce that Jeslin Varghese has joined the von Mentzer Lab as our new Lab Manager. Jeslin initially joined us as an intern through Jobbsprånget and has now transitioned into this new role.
<br />
Jeslin has a deep love for microbiology and has already become an important part of our team. We look forward to her continued contributions and are excited to see her grow with us.
<br /></p>]]></content><author><name>Astrid von Mentzer</name></author><category term="newcomers" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are happy to announce that Jeslin Varghese has joined the von Mentzer Lab as our new Lab Manager. Jeslin initially joined us as an intern through Jobbsprånget and has now transitioned into this new role. Jeslin has a deep love for microbiology and has already become an important part of our team. We look forward to her continued contributions and are excited to see her grow with us.]]></summary></entry></feed>