<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-08-05T18:27:23+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">vonMentzer-Group</title><subtitle>Website of the von Mentzer Group at the University of Gothenburg, led by Dr Astrid von Mentzer.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">von Mentzer Lab receives funding from Jeanssons Stiftelse</title><link href="/2023/12/01/fund-jeanssons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="von Mentzer Lab receives funding from Jeanssons Stiftelse" /><published>2023-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-05T18:26:28+00:00</updated><id>/2023/12/01/fund-jeanssons</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/12/01/fund-jeanssons.html"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>astrid_vonmentzer</name></author><category term="funding" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Postdoc Scholarship Available - Apply Now!</title><link href="/2023/08/20/postdoc-scholarship1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Postdoc Scholarship Available - Apply Now!" /><published>2023-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-05T18:26:28+00:00</updated><id>/2023/08/20/postdoc-scholarship1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/08/20/postdoc-scholarship1.html"><![CDATA[<p><br />
<br />
<strong>Are you interested in mocrobial genomics, virulence and antibiotic resistance?</strong>
<br />
<strong>Then you need to apply for the Postdoc Scholarship in the von Mentzer Lab!</strong>
<br />
<br />
Join us in experiencing the perfect blend of research and quality of life. Collaborate with leading minds, dive into innovative research, and create lasting connections within Sweden’s dynamic academic community.
<br />
<br />
Beyond academia, Sweden’s commitment to work-life balance ensures you’ll have time to explore the country’s captivating culture and natural beauty.
<br />
<br />
We can’t wait to welcome you to Sweden, where your academic journey will flourish.
<br />
<br />
Ready to seize this opportunity? Read more about our <a href="/Research">Research</a> and the <a href="/Team">Team</a> and how to apply <a href="https://www.nature.com/naturecareers/job/12804554/postdoctoral-scholarship-in-enterotoxigenic-e-coli-etec-genomics-and-evolution/">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Astrid von Mentzer</name></author><category term="job" /><category term="postdoc" /><category term="microbial genomics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Are you interested in mocrobial genomics, virulence and antibiotic resistance? Then you need to apply for the Postdoc Scholarship in the von Mentzer Lab! Join us in experiencing the perfect blend of research and quality of life. Collaborate with leading minds, dive into innovative research, and create lasting connections within Sweden’s dynamic academic community. Beyond academia, Sweden’s commitment to work-life balance ensures you’ll have time to explore the country’s captivating culture and natural beauty. We can’t wait to welcome you to Sweden, where your academic journey will flourish. Ready to seize this opportunity? Read more about our Research and the Team and how to apply here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring AMR - We will participate in the EMBO Plasmid Workshop</title><link href="/2023/08/18/embo-plasmid-workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring AMR - We will participate in the EMBO Plasmid Workshop" /><published>2023-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-05T18:26:28+00:00</updated><id>/2023/08/18/embo-plasmid-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/08/18/embo-plasmid-workshop.html"><![CDATA[<p><br />
<br />
We’re excited to share a lab update! I am gearing up for the EMBO Workshop, a deep dive into plasmid evolution and its connection to antimicrobial resistance (AMR).
<br />
<strong>Decoding Antibiotic Resistance Spread</strong>
<br />
Antimicrobial resistance is a global challenge, with bacteria becoming resistant to antibiotics. Plasmids, tiny genetic carriers, play a role by shuttling resistance genes between bacteria.
<br />
<strong>Unveiling Plasmid Secrets</strong>
<br />
At the EMBO Workshop, we’ll be exploring plasmid biology and ecology. Recent tech advancements allow us to better understand how plasmids contribute to AMR outbreaks.
<br />
<strong>Collaboration for Progress</strong>
The workshop is a hub of experts – from modelers to genetics researchers. I am thrilled to be part of this collaborative effort to address AMR challenges.
<br />
<strong>My Role in the Workshop</strong>
<br />
I’m eager to learn, contribute, and develop fresh approaches to tackle AMR. Stay tuned as we share insights from this enlightening experience.
<br />
<br />
Learn more about the workshop: <a href="https://meetings.embo.org/event/23-amr-plasmids">EMBO Plasmid workshop</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Astrid von Mentzer</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re excited to share a lab update! I am gearing up for the EMBO Workshop, a deep dive into plasmid evolution and its connection to antimicrobial resistance (AMR). Decoding Antibiotic Resistance Spread Antimicrobial resistance is a global challenge, with bacteria becoming resistant to antibiotics. Plasmids, tiny genetic carriers, play a role by shuttling resistance genes between bacteria. Unveiling Plasmid Secrets At the EMBO Workshop, we’ll be exploring plasmid biology and ecology. Recent tech advancements allow us to better understand how plasmids contribute to AMR outbreaks. Collaboration for Progress The workshop is a hub of experts – from modelers to genetics researchers. I am thrilled to be part of this collaborative effort to address AMR challenges. My Role in the Workshop I’m eager to learn, contribute, and develop fresh approaches to tackle AMR. Stay tuned as we share insights from this enlightening experience. Learn more about the workshop: EMBO Plasmid workshop]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Visiting the Thomson Group and joining the Applied Bioinformatics and Public Health Microbiology Conference</title><link href="/2023/05/01/applied_bioinfo_conf_and_meeting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visiting the Thomson Group and joining the Applied Bioinformatics and Public Health Microbiology Conference" /><published>2023-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-05T18:26:28+00:00</updated><id>/2023/05/01/applied_bioinfo_conf_and_meeting</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/05/01/applied_bioinfo_conf_and_meeting.html"><![CDATA[<p>It was a couple of years ago since I attended the <a href="https://coursesandconferences.wellcomeconnectingscience.org/event/applied-bioinformatics-public-health-microbiology-20230503/">Applied Bioinformatics and Public Health Conference</a> organised by Wellcome Connecting Science. Excited to get updated on the latest bioinformatic tools used in microbial genomics. One of the talks I am looking forward to a little bit extra is “Mutational spectra are associated with pathogen niche” by Chris Ruis.</p>]]></content><author><name>astrid_vonmentzer</name></author><category term="WIP," /><category term="conference" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It was a couple of years ago since I attended the Applied Bioinformatics and Public Health Conference organised by Wellcome Connecting Science. Excited to get updated on the latest bioinformatic tools used in microbial genomics. One of the talks I am looking forward to a little bit extra is “Mutational spectra are associated with pathogen niche” by Chris Ruis.]]></summary></entry></feed>